<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Virtual Document Management</title>
        <author>
            <personname><firstname>Ari</firstname><surname>Nordström</surname></personname>
            <email>ari.nordstrom@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>The idea to this paper originated partly from an earlier one I wrote for Balisage, and
            partly from the very real needs of a client. The Balisage paper was all about
            introducing a version management layer on top of the eXist-DB XML database's rather
            crude versioning module, to provide the principles of versioning management capable of
            separating the unnecessary versions that would happen whenever saving a document from
            the meaningful ones; very quickly there will be lots of versions of which most are of
            little interest later.</para>
        <para>The significant versions, therefore, will be very difficult to find, severely limiting
            the usability of the module.</para>
        <para>My client's needs, on the other hand, center on no real version management to begin
            with. The document editing and publishing workflow would perhaps be best described as
                <quote>distributed</quote>, comprising several systems between which a document
            would be sent on its way to being published in one or more of the multitude of systems
            outputting the content<footnote>
                <para>The systems range from several editing environments to a complex, multi-step
                    publishing chain that enriches and converts the informationending with several
                    different legacy output systems as well as a brand new one being
                    developed.</para>
            </footnote>. The problem here is that there is no single source system, no central
            system in control. Once published, there is no way to reliably trace a publication to
            its source to determine if there is a later and updated version of that document.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Version Management Concepts</title>
            <itemizedlist>
                <para>While this is not the place to offer a detailed discussion of version
                    management basics, it is nevertheless important to introduce and define a few
                    key concepts. None of these is new or original, but since the definitions and
                    their use vary depending on whom you ask, I will offer mine here:</para>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Anything can be versioned. Here, I will mostly infer XML documents, but
                        the paper applies to every kind of content.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>A new version happens when there is a significant change to the old. What
                            <quote>significant</quote> means may vary, of course, but at the core we
                        are talking about any kind of change to the information content or
                        structure. A spelling fix is an update, as is, of course, a reorganisation
                        of a section or an added paragraph.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Two different translations should not be seen as separate versions but
                        rather different renditions of the same basic document, much like GIF or JPG
                        renditions of an image.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Nor should two different output formats of the same document (say, PDF and
                        HTML) be seen as different versions. There might be good reasons to keep
                        track of them, but if their contents are the same, presentation should not
                        matter when determining their version.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Moving a document along document workflow stages (for example,
                            <quote>editing</quote>, <quote>reviewing</quote>,
                            <quote>translated</quote>, <quote>approved</quote> or
                            <quote>published</quote> should not automatically result in new
                        versions. A document could easily pass through them all without a single
                        change; on the other hand, multiple versions might be required for a single
                        stage such as <quote>editing</quote>. Therefore, <emphasis>workflow
                            handling, including lifecycle handling, should be kept separate from
                            version handling.</emphasis></para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Links, from paper-cross-references to hyperlinks, images or content
                        inclusions, should include the exact version and rendition<footnote>
                            <para>Meaning translation and, when relevant, the presentation.</para>
                        </footnote> of the target.</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Version <emphasis>labels</emphasis> are just that, labels. They help
                        readability but are not in themselves important. At their core, they are
                        simply numerals starting from 1.</para>
                    <para>Importance can be attached to them by introducing various business rules;
                        usually, the business rules help clarify workflow and lifecycle stages. For
                        example, <quote>1.0</quote> will frequently represent an approved and
                        published version (implying that <quote>0.9</quote> is a draft),
                            <quote>1.1</quote> a derivative of that version, usually without any
                        major changes to functionality, and so on.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>The Semantic Document</title>
            <para>Following my definitions, above, I would like to very briefly discuss the
                identification of documents, or more generically, resources.</para>
            <para>A filename is seldom unique or usable as a document identifier, so it is useful to
                create an abstraction for the document ID. Me, I'm partial to URNs, as they are
                straight-forward to use when implementing the above while allowing one to retain
                some of the readability of a filename.</para>
            <para>Imagine a <quote>document</quote> as a container of information about some
                subject. A base version of that document, disregarding versioning, workflow,
                presentation or language, might be identified as follows:</para>
            <programlisting>urn:x-myurn-ns:r1:mydocs:00001</programlisting>
            <para>What I'm saying here is simply that my document is, in this URN namespace,
                uniquely identified as <quote>mydocs:00001</quote>. It's an abstract document and
                only identifies the actual information, the document semantics. Adding a rendition
                language to the identifier could then be done like this:</para>
            <programlisting>urn:x-myurn-ns:r1:mydocs:00001:en-GB</programlisting>
            <para>This says that this particular rendition of the contents is in British
                English.</para>
            <para>Documents change over time, however, so to track that change, we introduce an a
                version label to the identifier:</para>
            <programlisting>urn:x-myurn-ns:r1:mydocs:00001:en-GB:1</programlisting>
            <para>Now, we can reliably track change to the document:</para>
            <programlisting>urn:x-myurn-ns:r1:mydocs:00001:en-GB:1
urn:x-myurn-ns:r1:mydocs:00001:en-GB:2
urn:x-myurn-ns:r1:mydocs:00001:en-GB:3
...</programlisting>
            <para>And if a version 10, say, was finally approved, we could translate that version to
                Finnish and identify the translation like so:</para>
            <programlisting>urn:x-myurn-ns:r1:mydocs:00001:fi-FI:10</programlisting>
            <para>If accepting the concepts as outlined here, it follows that this Finnish
                translation is identical to the British English
                    <code>urn:x-myurn-ns:r1:mydocs:00001:en-GB:10</code> document.</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The Problem</title>
        <para>So, the problem in a nutshell: </para>
        <para>Large numbers of XML documents are created, edited and published without a single,
            central source or proper version handling. Instead, they are moved from one system to
            another in a complex and multi-ended publishing chain, where no single system has
            control over a document in the sense that it can control an identifier namespace and
            uniquely identify a document passing through a step as the same one that went through an
            earlier step.</para>
        <!--Illustration of systems, crisscross of information-->
        <para>The various systems can be seen as a pipeline of loosely connected black boxes where
            the information is enriched and converted to other formats, eventually being published
            in Word ML on a customer PC or as content in a system intended to eventually be used as
            a central repository. </para>
        <para>The individual steps have control over the content while inside the black box
            representing the current step, but usually there is no way to query or track the content
            before or after the step. They tend to be fetched from a shared folder and delivered to
            another, and so there is no way to reliably track a single document through the
            publishing
            chain.<!-- It is not possible to reliably determine, based on a published document, if a later version with updated information exists of that document (such as a Word ML document on a customer's local hard disk) or what those changes are.--></para>
        <para>Yet, this is exactly what is required by the business; it must be possible to trace a
            document back to the previous steps, including the source, to find out if a later
            version exists, and what the changes are.</para>
        <para>Yet, many steps along the way have some degree of control over the document
                <emphasis>within that step</emphasis>. For example, most first steps in the chain<footnote>
                <para>Plural form; we are talking about several authoring systems.</para>
            </footnote>, where documents are authored, are database-driven. There is no actual
            versioning--a change to an existing document is done directly to that document so no old
            version is ever kept--but the system knows what changes are done to what document. It's
            just that no other later step, no black box in the publishing chain, can access or keep
            track of that information.</para>
        <para>While I would usually suggest introducing a single-source document management system
            to handle the situation - something that can uniquely identify and version handle every
            piece of content, and introduce workflows and steps to maintain complete control over
            the document throughout the publishing chain - this is, for various reasons, not
            feasible.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>The Solution</title>
        <para>Instead, I suggest introducing a passive tracking system to track every observable
            event when a document passes through the publishing chain. This system would log every
            transaction in every output and every input of every black box, identifying as much
            information of the transaction as possible and adding any available data about the
            document itself, but also about the system, from timestamps to local identifiers, any
            identity transforms happning between the input and the output, and so on.</para>
        <para>By logging events happening to a document throughout the publishing chain, the
            tracking system is able to construct a workflow history for that document, identifying
            changes being done to the document when publishing it. </para>
        <!--Illustration, version logging-->
        <para>Importantly, when a document in the database in the first step is updated, this
            information is passed on to the tracking system that is then able to recognise that the
            new event happens to a document already being tracked, and can therefore build a
            versioning history for that document.</para>
        <para>The tracking system should ideally log the tracking events in an XML document that
            models a workflow and versioning history for a resource. An XML database such as eXist
            would be ideally suited to do the job.</para>
        <para>The versioning XML, as proposed in my Balisage paper (see XXX), looks like
            this:</para>
        <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
&lt;resource>
    
    &lt;!-- Base URN -->
    &lt;base>&lt;/base>
    
    &lt;!-- Integer version 1 -->
    &lt;version>
        &lt;rev>1&lt;/rev>
        &lt;url lang="en-GB">&lt;/url>
        &lt;metadata>
            ...
        &lt;/metadata>
        
        &lt;!-- 1st decimal version -->
        &lt;version>
            &lt;rev>1&lt;/rev>
            &lt;url>&lt;/url>
            &lt;metadata>
                ...
            &lt;/metadata>
        &lt;/version>
        
        &lt;!-- 2d decimal version -->
        &lt;version>
            &lt;rev>2&lt;/rev>
            &lt;url lang="en-GB">&lt;/url>
            &lt;url lang="sv-SE">&lt;/url>
            &lt;url lang="fi-FI">&lt;/url>
            &lt;metadata>
                ...
            &lt;/metadata>
        &lt;/version>
    &lt;/version>
    
    &lt;!-- Integer version 2 -->
    &lt;version>
        &lt;rev>2&lt;/rev>
        &lt;url lang="en-GB">&lt;/url>
        &lt;url lang="sv-SE">&lt;/url>
        &lt;url lang="fi-FI">&lt;/url>
        &lt;metadata>
            ...
        &lt;/metadata>
        
        &lt;!-- Stage 1 (decimal versions) -->
        &lt;version>
            &lt;rev>1&lt;/rev>
            &lt;url>&lt;/url>
            &lt;metadata>
                ...
            &lt;/metadata>
        &lt;/version>
        &lt;version>
            &lt;rev>2&lt;/rev>
            &lt;url>&lt;/url>
            &lt;metadata>
                ...
            &lt;/metadata>
        &lt;/version>
    &lt;/version>
&lt;/resource>
</programlisting>
        <para>The tracking system creates an identifier in the form of a URN, used to uniquely
            identify a single resource originating from the first step in the publishing chain. This
            identifier is guaranteed to be unique in the tracking system, but is not known by any of
            the participating steps in the publishing chain that is being tracked, or indeed by the
            document itself; it is simply a common name for a resource being followed across the
            chain.</para>
        <para>The URN above includes a two-level versioning component (i.e. <quote>1.0</quote>,
                <quote>1.1</quote>, <quote>1.2</quote>, etc) to indicate the progress of the
            resource across the publishing chain. The first level, the integer level, is created
            when the document is first created (or rather, when the first transaction involving the
            document is logged by the tracking system, which is probably when a completed version
            leaves the first step), and the decimal versions identify the subsequent transactions
            logged on that document.</para>
        <para>The second version is the first logged transaction of an updated version of the
            document in the first integer version, and the decimal versions added to that are the
            transactions logged after that.</para>
        <para>The <tag>metadata</tag> structure contains step-specific information about the
            resource and about the system(s) involved in that particular step, including local URLs,
            local document IDs, and so on. This information can be used later to retrieve versioning
            or workflow history about a resource at that point in time, especially if the local
            system is capable of answering queries based on say, the local document ID.</para>
        <para>The result is a versioning and workflow history of a resource based on the events
            happening to it along the publishing chain. It can by no means replace a complete
            version <emphasis>handling</emphasis> system since none of the <quote>versions</quote>
            that happen along the way is saved and cannot be retrieved later.</para>
        <para>Of course, the tracking system could easily store any relevant contents of the tracked
            document, from skeletal structure of the XML to the complete document itself, at any
            point in the publishing chain, most usefully, perhaps, when logging the first and last
            steps of the publishing chain. This would in effect create a versioning system of sorts,
            a virtual document management system where changes to the content can be tracked and
            queried. </para>
        <para>In the current, decentralised series of systems, it is next to impossible to find out
            if there is a later version of a document, or what the changes are between the two. The
            tracking system outlined here can log the transactions leading up to the two end
            versions of the document, use the logs to find out what changes were made, either by
            direct comparison if the sources leading to the two versions are stored by the tracking
            system, or by displaying any stored metadata about the changes.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Implementation and Use</title>
        <para>Ideally, the tracking system is implemented using an XML database, as it makes it easy
            to build the XML-based versioning and workflow structures, and to query them later. An
            XML database can be used to store the tracked content itself, if desired.</para>
        <para>The system needs to be a passive observer, in that it cannot control or change any of
            the content it tracks, but the tracked systems (<quote>steps</quote>, in the above
            parlance) all require some additional functionality that allows them to log the
            transactions. Essentially, this functionality would be a service that logs metadata
            about the originating system (system ID, timestamps, users, etc), the document (ID in
            the originating system, URL), but also any other available information about the
            transaction (such as automated comments or information entered by a user when initiating
            the transaction or event). Once completed, the information would then be passed along to
            the tracking system, initiating a change to an existing versioning XML, or perhaps a new
            versioning instance altogether.</para>
        <para>The versioning information stored by the tracking system can be used by any of the
            participating systems to present an overview of the versioning and workflow history The
            overview can also be queried by the participating systems.</para>
        <para>Also, consider the case where a document is sent to two <emphasis>parallel publishing
                outputs</emphasis> where the requirements of one output differ from the other's,
            forcing the editor updating the document in <quote>step one</quote> to change the
            contents slightly for the two outputs. In effect, this is a <quote>fork</quote>, a split
            of the contents happening because of differing requirements, where, without a document
            management system, it is very difficult to keep track of, and update, the
            variants.</para>
        <programlisting>TBA: XML example of "fork" for two outputs</programlisting>
        <para>The tracking system would simply track any transactions leading up to the respective
            variant, log the variations in forked but related versioning XML, and allow the editor
            to maintain the relationship between the two. The tracking system would keep track of
            both outputs, and also allow the end user to keep track of any relevant changes (in
            effect, only the changes affecting his output rather than the changes affecting the
            other).</para>
        <!--Presentation of versioning: web page version of the XML, with hyperlinks and other functionality (diff, searches, etc)
Make available to editors, end users-->
    </section>
    <bibliography>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="id-ml-versioning">Nordström, Ari. “Multilevel Versioning.” Presented at
            Balisage: The Markup Conference 2014, Washington, DC, August 5 - 8, 2014. In Proceedings
            of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2014. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 13
            (2014). doi:10.4242/BalisageVol13.Nordstrom01.</bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
</article>
