<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbookxi.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/rng/docbook.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
        xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0">
    <info>
        <title>Virtual Document Management</title>
        <author>
            <personname><firstname>Ari</firstname><surname>Nordström</surname></personname>
            <email>ari.nordstrom@gmail.com</email>
        </author>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Extended Abstract</title>
        <para>Note: This <quote>paper</quote> is just an extended abstract of sorts. The idea
            originated partly from an earlier paper I wrote for Balisage, and partly the very real
            needs of a client. I intend to flesh out the solution that is outlined here, both in
            terms of the markup and in terms of the functionality required.</para>
        <section>
            <title>Problem</title>
            <para>Problem: Large numbers of XML documents are created, edited and published without
                a single, central source or proper version handling. Instead, they are moved from
                one system to another, where no single system can be seen as the source; no system
                has control over a document in the sense that it can control an identifier namespace
                and uniquely identify a document passing through a step in the publishing chain as
                the same one that went through an earlier step.</para>
            <para>The various systems can be seen as a pipeline of loosely connected black boxes
                where the information is enriched and converted to other formats, eventually being
                published in Word ML on a customer PC or as content in a system intended to be used
                as a central repository. The individual steps have control over the content while
                inside that black box, but usually no way to query or track the content before or
                after the step. This means that there is no way to reliably track a single document
                through the publishing chain, and therefore it is not possible to reliably
                determine, based on a published document, if a later version with updated
                information exists of that document (such as a Word ML document on a customer's
                local hard disk) or what those changes are.</para>
            <para>Yet, many steps along the way have some degree of control over the document
                    <emphasis>within that step</emphasis>. For example, the first step in the chain,
                where documents are authored, is database-driven. There is no actual versioning--a
                change to an existing document is done directly to that document so no old version
                is ever kept--but the system knows what changes are done to what document. It's just
                that no other later step, no black box in the publishing chain, can access or keep
                track of that information.</para>
            <para>While I would usually suggest introducing a single-source document management
                system to handle the situation - something that can uniquely identify and version
                handle every piece of content, and introduce workflows and steps to maintain
                complete control over the document throughout the publishing chain - this is, for
                various reasons, not feasible.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Solution</title>
            <para>Instead, I suggest introducing a passive tracking system to track every observable
                event when a document passes through the publishing chain. This system would log
                every transaction in every output and every input of every black box, identifying as
                much information of the transaction as possible and adding any available data about
                the document itself, but also about the system, from timestamps to local
                identifiers, any identity transforms happning between the input and the output, and
                so on.</para>
            <para>By logging events happening to a document throughout the publishing chain, the
                tracking system is able to construct a workflow history for that document,
                identifying changes being done to the document when publishing it. </para>
            <para>But even more importantly, when a document in the database in the first step is
                updated, this information is passed on to the tracking system that is then able to
                recognise that the new event happens to a document already being tracked, and can
                therefore build a versioning history for that document.</para>
            <para>The tracking system should ideally log the tracking events in an XML document that
                models a workflow and versioning history for a resource. An XML database such as
                eXist would be ideally suited to do the job.</para>
            <para>The versioning XML looks (more or less) like this:</para>
            <programlisting>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
&lt;resource>
    
    &lt;!-- Base URN -->
    &lt;base>&lt;/base>
    
    &lt;!-- Integer version 1 -->
    &lt;version>
        &lt;rev>1&lt;/rev>
        &lt;url lang="en-GB">&lt;/url>
        &lt;metadata>
            ...
        &lt;/metadata>
        
        &lt;!-- 1st decimal version -->
        &lt;version>
            &lt;rev>1&lt;/rev>
            &lt;url>&lt;/url>
            &lt;metadata>
                ...
            &lt;/metadata>
        &lt;/version>
        
        &lt;!-- 2d decimal version -->
        &lt;version>
            &lt;rev>2&lt;/rev>
            &lt;url lang="en-GB">&lt;/url>
            &lt;url lang="sv-SE">&lt;/url>
            &lt;url lang="fi-FI">&lt;/url>
            &lt;metadata>
                ...
            &lt;/metadata>
        &lt;/version>
    &lt;/version>
    
    &lt;!-- Integer version 2 -->
    &lt;version>
        &lt;rev>2&lt;/rev>
        &lt;url lang="en-GB">&lt;/url>
        &lt;url lang="sv-SE">&lt;/url>
        &lt;url lang="fi-FI">&lt;/url>
        &lt;metadata>
            ...
        &lt;/metadata>
        
        &lt;!-- Stage 1 (decimal versions) -->
        &lt;version>
            &lt;rev>1&lt;/rev>
            &lt;url>&lt;/url>
            &lt;metadata>
                ...
            &lt;/metadata>
        &lt;/version>
        &lt;version>
            &lt;rev>2&lt;/rev>
            &lt;url>&lt;/url>
            &lt;metadata>
                ...
            &lt;/metadata>
        &lt;/version>
    &lt;/version>
&lt;/resource>
</programlisting>
            <para>The tracking system creates an identifier (here in the form of a URN) used to
                uniquely identify a single resource originating from the first step in the
                publishing chain. This identifier is guaranteed to be unique in the tracking system,
                but is not known by any of the participating steps in the publishing chain that is
                being tracked; it is simply a common name for a resource being followed across the
                chain.</para>
            <para>The URN includes a two-level versioning component (i.e. <quote>1.0</quote>,
                    <quote>1.1</quote>, <quote>1.2</quote>, etc) to indicate the progress of the
                resource across the publishing chain. The first level, the integer level, is created
                when the document is first created (or rather, when the first transaction involving
                the document is logged by the tracking system, which is probably when a completed
                version leaves the first step), and the decimal versions identify the subsequent
                transactions logged on that document.</para>
            <para>The second version is the first logged transaction of an updated version of the
                document in the first integer version, and the decimal versions added to that are
                the transactions logged after that.</para>
            <para>The <tag>metadata</tag> structure contains step-specific information about the
                resource and about the system(s) involved in that particular step, including local
                URLs, local document IDs, and so on. This information can be used later to retrieve
                versioning or workflow history about a resource at that point in time, especially if
                the local system is capable of answering queries based on say, the local document
                ID.</para>
            <para>The result is a versioning and workflow history of a resource based on the events
                happening to it along the publishing chain. It can by no means replace a complete
                version <emphasis>handling</emphasis> system since none of the
                    <quote>versions</quote> that happen along the way is saved and cannot be
                retrieved later.</para>
            <para>Of course, the tracking system could easily store any relevant contents of the
                tracked document, from skeletal structure of the XML to the complete document
                itself, at any point in the publishing chain, most usefully, perhaps, when logging
                the first and last steps of the publishing chain. This would in effect create a
                versioning system of sorts, a virtual document management system where changes to
                the content can be tracked and queried. </para>
            <para>As mentioned above, a problem with the current, decentralised series of systems
                where no single system is in control is that it is next to impossible to find out if
                there is a later version of a document, or what the changes are between the two. The
                tracking system outlined here can log the transactions leading up to the two end
                versions of the document, use the logs to find out what changes were made, either by
                direct comparison if the sources leading to the two versions were stored by the
                tracking system, or by displaying any stored metadata about the changes.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Implementation and Use</title>
            <para>The tracking system is ideally an XML database, as it makes it easy to build the
                XML-based versioning and workflow information, and to query it later, but also
                because it can be used to store the tracked content itself, if desired.</para>
            <para>The system needs to be a passive observer, in that it canot control or change any
                of the content it tracks, but the tracked systems (<quote>steps</quote>, in the
                above parlance) all require some additional functionality that allows them to log
                the transactions. Essentially, this functionality would be a service that logs
                metadata about the originating system (system ID, timestamps, users, etc), the
                document (ID in the originating system, URL), but also any other available
                information about the transaction (such as automated comments or information entered
                by a user when initiating the transaction or event). Once completed, the information
                would then be passed along to the tracking system, initiating a change to an
                existing versioning XML, or perhaps a new versioning instance altogether.</para>
            <para>The versioning information stored by the tracking system can be used by any of the
                participating systems to present an overview of the versioning and workflow history
                The overview can also be queried by the participating systems.</para>
            <para>Also, consider the case where a document is sent to two <emphasis>parallel
                    publishing outputs</emphasis> where the requirements of one output differ from
                the other's, forcing the editor updating the document in <quote>step one</quote> to
                change the contents slightly for the two outputs. In effect, this is a
                    <quote>fork</quote>, a split of the contents happening because of differing
                requirements, where, without a document management system, it is very difficult to
                keep track of, and update, the variants.</para>
            <programlisting>TBA: XML example of "fork" for two outputs</programlisting>
            <para>The tracking system would simply track any transactions leading up to the
                respective variant, log the variations in forked but related versioning XML, and
                allow the editor to maintain the relationship between the two. The tracking system
                would keep track of both outputs, and also allow the end user to keep track of any
                relevant changes (in effect, only the changes affecting his output rather than the
                changes affecting the other).</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <bibliography>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="id-ml-versioning">Nordström, Ari. “Multilevel Versioning.” Presented at
            Balisage: The Markup Conference 2014, Washington, DC, August 5 - 8, 2014. In Proceedings
            of Balisage: The Markup Conference 2014. Balisage Series on Markup Technologies, vol. 13
            (2014). doi:10.4242/BalisageVol13.Nordstrom01.</bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
</article>
